<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful and true witenss to the light of Jesus Christ, or, Word of faith within in the heart and conscience proving that God alwayes did, and doth reveal himself in it, and through it to the sons and daughters of men, that they may believe and be saved ... : also a postscript in answer to some base lyes and reflections cast upon me by William Haworth, an independent preacher / Christopher Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25802</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09135147</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09135147</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42502</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42502)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1295:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful and true witenss to the light of Jesus Christ, or, Word of faith within in the heart and conscience proving that God alwayes did, and doth reveal himself in it, and through it to the sons and daughters of men, that they may believe and be saved ... : also a postscript in answer to some base lyes and reflections cast upon me by William Haworth, an independent preacher / Christopher Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42502:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42502:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Faithful and True WITNESS TO THE LIGHT OF Ieſus Chriſt, or Word of Faith WITHIN, in the Heart and Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Proving that God alwayes did, and doth reveal himſelf in it, and through it to the Sons and Daughters of Men, that they may believe, and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>And that no People ever knew God or themſelves in any Meaſure, in any Age or Generation, under any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation or Miniſtration whatſoever, but in this Word of Faith, that through it they might believe and be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Poſtſcript, in Anſwer to ſome baſe Lyes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections caſt upon me by <hi>William Haworth,</hi> an <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> Preacher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42502:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42502:2"/>
            <head>A Faithful &amp; True WITNESS TO THE Light of Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO you all Profeſſors and People a Word of Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you turn in your Minds to the Light of Jeſus Chriſt within, in your Conſciences, that with it you may ſee where you are, and find the true Way to Everlaſting Life, and do not call that natural in Oppoſition to the Light and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, which revealeth to Man his Thoughts, and lets him ſee the Intents of his Heart, whether they be good or evil, and all that ever he doth; for no other Way can any Man come to the Knowledge of God, or of himſelf, but by this Means; neither did ever any Man know God, but by this Way, Chriſt, the Way, Truth and Life, who enlightneth every Man that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the World; this was the Word of Faith in <hi>Adam</hi>'s Heart, whereby he knew what God required of him in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radical State, it was the Word of his Underſtanding and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and in this there was Power to have preſerved him, if he had truſted, and ſtaid his Mind in it, and in it he had known no Evil, but in the Eternal Sence of the Love, Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Creator he had been preſerved, but going from this he fell into Sin and Tranſgreſſion of the Mind of the Lord, and was aſhamed, becauſe that which he fell from, and turned from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42502:3"/>
the Counſel of, revealed unto him his Sin and his Nakedneſs, and then he would have hid himſelf to have eſcaped Shame and Condemnation; ſo that here was his Condemnation, the Light, and is the Condemnation of all in him, and with this Light all the Sons of the diſobedient old <hi>Adam</hi> are found out, whether they be Profeſſors or Prophane; and it is in vain for any to hide themſelves under any Pretence or Profeſſion of Religion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; for they will be found out, condemned, and be made aſhamed, and their Nakedneſs will appear.</p>
            <p>Oh all ye Profeſſors and Prophane, conſider and hearken to the Counſel of God in the Light, be wiſe-hearted, and learn in it firſt to know your Eſtate and Inward Condition, and alſo to know the Lord, the Seed of the Woman to bruiſe the Scrpent's Head; for by this Principle he doth, and ever did ſpeak to Mankind in general, even to their Hearts and Conſciences; and it was the true Word of Faith in their Hearts, when God ſpake to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who ſpoak forth the Scriptures as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt; and in this Principle, the Light or Word of Faith, they received the holy Doctrine of God by this Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit and Guide, raiſed up to open their Underſtandings, by which they knew the Lord, and the Revelation of his Mind, what they were to ſpeak or reveal to any People; it was the ſame in that Day, the Light of God, or Chriſt, the Word of true Faith; and if any would nicely diſtinguiſh, and ſay, it was the Light of God the Father or Creator, but not of Chriſt the Saviour and Redeemer; I anſwer, the Lord God made the World by the ſame Word that was in the Beginning with God, and was God, which Word became Fleſh, in whom was Life, and the Life was the Light of Men; and ſo <hi>God made all Things by him, and without him was nothing made that was made, and all Power in Heaven and Earth is given to him,</hi> Mat. 28. 18. <hi>And all Judgment,</hi> Joh. 5. 22. Neither can there be Eternal Judgment without him, in the Hearts and Conſciences of Men; therefore it is abſurd to ſay, <hi>It is not the ſpiritual ſaving Light of Jeſus Chriſt, the Word or Son of God;</hi> for if it be a Light that either judges or condemns for Sin within, or ſaves from it, then it is the Light of Chriſt, and no other, and therefore ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42502:3"/>
and ſaving, and powerful in the working, and a Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of it to all that believe, becauſe it is a Meaſure of and from the living God and his Eternal Powerful Word and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and is piercing and ſearching within to diſcover unto Man his Sin, though never ſo ſecr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, and with it and in it God tryes Mens Hearts and Reins, and God's Eternal Judgment is ſet up in it.</p>
            <p>And therefore this is to check the Abſurdity of that baſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection caſt upon it by many who profeſs to teach others the Way of God, who ſay, <hi>It is a Natural Light, in Oppoſition to the Spiritual Light of Chriſt;</hi> and herein they manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict their own Doctrine, who in Word preach for Doctrine and ſay, <hi>Chriſt is all in all,</hi> and confeſs, <hi>That all Judgment is delivered to the Son,</hi> and yet deny it again; and yet moſt of them confeſs <hi>that to be true Judgment ſet up in the Hearts of Men and Women by this Light within;</hi> and hereby they confeſs <hi>People may read their Condemnation,</hi> and that <hi>it judges People for their inward Thoughts, Words and Deeds,</hi> and yet they call this <hi>Natural,</hi> and cry down the Spirituality of it, as from Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo derogate from their own Doctrine and Chriſt's Authority, who imagine another Judgment ſet up in the Heart and Conſcience before Chriſt come by a Natural Light, and if ſo, then all Power and Judgment is not committed to the Son, neither is Chriſt as to Mans Salvation or Condemnation all in all; and therefore they are in the Dark, groping for the Light at Noon day, and put Natural for Spiritual; for the Light muſt needs be ſpiritual, which judgeth the ſpiritual Matters of a Man's Heart and Conſcience, his ſecreteſt Thoughts of his Heart that ever he thought, his Affections and his Inteutions, which are all Spiritual, or from a Man's Spirit, to be judged or diſcerned by no Natural Man or Natural Thing.</p>
            <p>All will grant, <hi>That no Man knows the particular Thoughts and Intents of another Man's Heart, as relating to Good or Evil, but by the Revelation of Gods Spirit;</hi> therefore it muſt needs be the Revelation of God's Spirit and Light within, that makes manifeſt to a Man his own inward Thoughts and ſpiritual Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, that he may diſcern whether they be good or evil.</p>
            <p>So this Light and Manifeſtation of the Spirit of God was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42502:4"/>
the ſame in its Nature, it never changed nor ever will, but ſtood and ſtands a Witneſs for God in all Ages and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to witneſs againſt the Evil in all Ages and Generations, and for the Good; and to every Diſpenſation and Miniſtrarion of God, that in whatſoever Time they lived, they might know how to chuſe the Good, and refuſe the Evil; and through this Inward Light <hi>Abraham</hi> knew the Voice of God that ſpake to him, and that it was the Voice of God, and that it was not a Deluſion, when he was called out of his own Country, he had Power, waiting upon God in this Principle, to try the Spirits, and to diſcern the Voice and Teaching of the true Spirit of God; he had no other Teacher but the Lord in this Light; and God commanded him to offer up his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and he obeyed, and had Power ſo to do in this Light, ſo that the Word of his Faith was nigh him, even in his Heart and Mouth to obey the Precepts and Commands of God in it; ſo that Chriſt was then his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whom he believed in and obeyed, and was the Shepherd and Biſhop of his Soul, whoſe Day in the Light he ſaw, and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; for God's Manifeſtations and Heavenly Operations were all then in and through Chriſt, and Salvation then was in him, and in no other, for God never revealed or wrought any Work without him; and the holy Men of God then were made holy by no other Power, but the Power of Chriſt revealed in the Light, ſo that by this Light and the Manifeſtation of the Spirit within, they knew how to diſtinguiſh betwixt the true and falſe Righteouſneſs in all Ages, and the true and falſe Spirit, and what they both led and moved unto; and ſo the Holy Men reproved the Wicked in all Ages, and were God's faithful Witneſſes, for they feared him, and waited upon him, and he poured forth of his Spirit upon them, and they received the Gift of it in all Ages, ſo far as God was pleaſed to make it manifeſt, and they were impowred with it to do the Lord's Will, and they were a ſpiritual People, and led by the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of God in their Wayes and Works, and there were ſpiritual <hi>Jews</hi> in meaſure, which worſhipped God in the Spirit, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence was in God, and not in the Fleſh, or in the Arm of it: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in meaſure knew God's Spirit and Power in that Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it was the Lord that guided him and conducted him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42502:4"/>
in his going out in his Name againſt <hi>Goliah</hi> without Sword or Spear; for he went out in the Faith and Strength of God, and prevailed, and he knew the Lord was with him, by the Word of his Faith, wherein God ſhewed him his great Authority and Power which he ſhould ſtand in, and overcome that <hi>Goliah;</hi> and the Spirit of God came upon many, and they did and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many wonderful Things, by the Help and Aſſiſtance of God in the Light, ſo that they were Witneſſes of the living God, and Power of Eternal Salvation, or of that Eternal Word that became Fleſh; ſo that in thoſe ancient Dayes what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to his People or Prophets, it was in the Light within, and Principle we now direct People to; and never was there any Revelation or Diſpenſation of God, or Operation of his Power, but it was in his own Light, both before the Law, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and in this Day of his more ſpiritual Appearance; and in Chriſt was the Acceptation in all Ages, as People feared God, and wrought Righteouſneſs; ſo that they in their Day that worſhipped God in the Spirit, ſo far as God was pleaſed to reveal himſelf, and ſtrictly require of them, were accepted, and the diſobedient rejected; and the true Worſhippers among the <hi>Jews</hi> had their Acceptation in Chriſt, whereby they were impowered with a Meaſure of his Spirit, to offer their Hearts to God; and when at any Time they offered the Offerings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired under that Diſpenſation with a perfect and true Heart, in the Fear and Love of God, they were accepted, becauſe they rightly and honeſtly obeyed the Lord in ſuch his Requirings, and ſuch grew into further inward Diſcoveries of the Subſtance, whenas on the contrary, they that were ſinful and hypocritical, though in the Letter and Form of that Worſhip, they might offer, and do the ſame Thing in Shew and Appearance, yet it was abominable, they not being the true People of God, but only made a Shew then of being ſo, &amp; were then the hypocritical and falſe-hearted <hi>Jews,</hi> their Offering and Service not proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a pure, but a polluted Mind and Heart, rejecting the Counſel of God in the Light or Word of Faith in their Hearts, which convinced them of Sin, and in which the Lord ſet before them Life and Death, which Counſel they rejected, and lived then in the bare Form of Godlineſs, but not in the Power; ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42502:5"/>
in that ſinful Nature living, though in the Dayes of Chriſt the <hi>Phariſees</hi> flouriſhed exceedingly in the Profeſſion of that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of <hi>Moſes,</hi> according to the Letter or Form of it, that when Chriſt the Subſtance came, they oppoſed him, and ſo were made manifeſt to be of the Devil, <hi>becauſe they loved their Evil Deeds, and hated the Light;</hi> and in that Mind and State of ſinful inward Hypocriſie, they did as naturally op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lord Jeſus in his Appearance in that Body at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as they did that Manifeſtation of his Appearance in their own Conſciences, which convinced them of Sin, and called them out of it.</p>
            <p>So they that fear'd God in the Dayes of <hi>Moſes</hi> were led with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to the Subſtance of all thoſe Types and Shadows and outward Repreſentations whatſoever; and <hi>by the Interpretation and Teaching of the Word of Faith in their Hearts, they were inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Myſtery of Salvation it ſelf, the better Hope, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, and came to ſee what thoſe outward Shadows ſignified under the Law, and whereunto they ſerved;</hi> as Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, after he had ſpoken forth Parables to the People, they inquiring the Meaning of the Parables, <hi>To you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom, but to others in Parables:</hi> So to them under the Law, who feared God, and attended to the <hi>Word of Faith within, to them it was given to know the true Meaning of thoſe Types; and what they ſignified and ſerved unto, and their true and right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> and they were his true People then, ſerving the Lord according to the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his Will under that Diſpenſation, and they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly made <hi>Holy by the inward Power of Chriſt, and were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted there in their Holy and Evangelical Faith and Living, ſo far as the Lord was pleaſed to open that great Myſtery in them, and to them; for without Faith in Chriſt then, the Subſtance, who was to come in that bodily Appearance at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>it was as impoſſible to pleaſe God as now; and by that Faith they were ſav'd and accepted, for the bare Obſervance of the Letter of the Law made nothing Perſect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this is the Sum of what I have to ſay in this Matter, in all Ages and Generations the Lord hath afforded the Means of Salvation, even in the Dayes of the greateſt Ignorance that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42502:5"/>
ever was in the World, which he is ſaid to wink at, yea, amongſt the <hi>Gentiles, that which might be known of God was manifeſt in them, for he ſhewed it unto them,</hi> Rom. 1. 19. even the Light of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, that true Light which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World, which was the Cauſe of the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Wrath of God from Heaven againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men, who held the Truth in Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 18. For the very <hi>Gentiles were l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt without Excuſe, becauſe when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, &amp;c.</hi> Ver. 21. Here therefore is the Means to all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general, the Word of Faith in their Hearts that they may believe and underſtand what God requires of them in their Day and Time; and they in all Ages that have feared God, and eſchewed Evil, ſo far as they were convinced in their Hearts by this Principle of God's abſolute Requirings, and joyned their Hearts to this Principle, truſting in it, and refuſing the Evil, though they did not know the Name of it in ſuch Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as we do in this Day, yet in Meaſure they were Believers and Partakers of the Vertue of it, by Means whereof they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Strength, and were kept from Evil, and were God's Witneſſes, and reproved the Wickedneſs of the Times they lived in, and in that they knew not ſo much of God as after-Generations had revealed unto them, yet they wore accepted in their faithful Obedience to what they knew in their Day, and was neceſſarily required of them.</p>
            <p>So that the Word of Faith was teſtified unto by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Day, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 11, 12, 13, 14. And it was the ſame Word of Faith which the Apoſtles preached, <hi>Rom. 10. 6, 7, 8, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore it was the ſame in the Day of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Word of their Faith, that they might believe and obey the Lord's Commands; and in all Times, Miniſtrations and Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it was the ſame, and it was God's ſpiritual Witneſs in the Apoſtles Dayes, when they preached their Spiritual, Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Heavenly Goſpel, there was a Witneſs in Peoples Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, when they preached their Goſpel (mark that) they had their Witneſs in every Man's Conſcience, which evidenced and witneſſed the Truth of the Apoſtles Doctrine, though they rejected it, and therefore with this Light they were condemned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42502:6"/>
for their Unbelief, and the Apoſtle was clear of their Blood, and of the Blood of all Men, becauſe they would not hear or regard the Goſpel preaching, though they were capacitated by this Word of Faith to have believed and obeyed it, but they whoſe Hearts did not believe to Righteouſneſs, were ſuch as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their <hi>Evil Deeds, and hated the Light, and it was their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the malicious Sottiſhneſs of ſome profeſſed Preachers of that they call Goſpel, who are notorious Wicked againſt the Truth, and in my hearing have called this bleſſed Light of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>altogether Darkneſs;</hi> whither will not Malice tranſport People? ſo that what Blaſphemy will they not utter, who hate the Lord's Chriſt, and his bleſſed Appearance?</p>
            <p>Oh Rebellious Teachers, and Blind Leaders of the People, who drag the People into Miſchief, inſtead of bringing them unto Chriſt, or turning them to his Light, that they may believe and be ſaved; the Hand of the Lord is againſt ſuch <hi>vain Bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and filthy Teachers, who deny the Lord that bought them, and tread his precious Blood under their wicked Feet, and will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enter themſelves</hi> (into the Goſpel-Faith) <hi>that they may be ſaved, nor ſuffer others to enter,</hi> whom they can hinder: I ſpeak this of ſuch wicked ſhameleſs Zealots as have ſold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to do wickedly, and are not aſhamed in the Face of the whole World to oppoſe the Light within, in Malice and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, whatever it coſts them; yea, they are as wicked as the worſt of Chriſt's Enemies ever were, who cryed, <hi>Away with him, Crucifie him, his Blood be upon us and our Children: with what Force have they endeavoured in like Manner to deſtroy the Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and quench the Spirit, Breath and Life of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it may be ſome of thoſe in former Times were by this very Principle they ſo perfectly oppoſe, convinced of Sin, and then had ſome Sence of the VVeight of their Iniquities upon them; and in that Day there might be ſome Tenderneſs wrought in them, and they might have Openings of Light and Truth, ſo far as to let them ſee there was a Neceſſity of ſeparating from the Sin, of the Times they lived in, and from their VVayes and VVorſhips, and the Lord owned them as they feared him, and were an enquiring People after him then, and they had ſome of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42502:6"/>
them Openings of further Diſcoveries at Hand, and glorious Times to come; and they would ſpeak of the Teaching of the Spirit within, and a VVork within, and were a breathing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and there was ſome Greenneſs amongſt them, and they were in Meaſure hated and perſecuted, and all this; and if they had had a Thouſand Times more Experience of God, it was by and through this Light, and pure VVord of Faith, as God opened to them in it; but departing from this Inward Light and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſitting down in the Form of that, which in ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree they had had ſome Taſt of, and not waiting in Tenderneſs, in that Light and Spirit which opened good Things unto them, and let them ſee that bleſſed Things were at Hand, to be revealed, and further Manifeſtations of God in Chriſt, they fell from their State, and departed from the Light and Spirit within, and loſt their Strength to withſtand the Enemy, and ſo he got Power over them, and in Heart they have backſlided and in that State they have rebelled againſt the Lord and his Truth in their own Particulars, and found out a VVay to excuſe themſelves, by calling themſelves <hi>Believers</hi> in a State of Sin, <hi>and Chriſt dyed for them, and they are the Elect of God,</hi> and the like, <hi>and God imputes Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to them, and ſees no Sin in them, but looks upon them in Chriſt, though the Enemy bears the Rule, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the Heart;</hi> a meer Cheat; but if they had ſtood in God's Heavenly Light and Counſel, he would by his Eternal Almighty Power ſoon have ſubdued Sin under them, and they would have witneſſed <hi>Chriſt in them, the Hope of Glory, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then he that is in the World,</hi> and have known the VVork of true Regeneration and Peace, and not have needed ſuch vain Covets and Beggarly Shifts as now they are got into, and with the <hi>Phariſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſay, they ſee,</hi> and yet their Sin remains in their Hearts, ſpiritually perſecuting the dear Lord Jeſus; yea, if they had kept to their firſt Integrity, and waited in the Light, they would have been able to have read God's pure living Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations with his People in this the Day of his pure Power; but it is hid from the Eyes of ſuch who are at preſent wilfully bent, and ſet to oppoſe the Light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Here is Law and Goſpel to be revealed ſpiritually in the Light, the Promiſe witneſſed the promiſed Seed, the Power of God to Salvation, made manifeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42502:7"/>
the ſame, witneſſed in this Light, that <hi>both kills and makes alive, the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus, that makes free from the Law of Sin and Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh bleſſed are they that believe in this Light, that they may be the Children of it, through the true Judgment that is in it, they will come to know the Myſtery of Eternal Salvation, and reſt with the Lamb for everm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps will object and ſay, <hi>Why did Chriſt Jeſus ſay to his Diſciples, he would ſend them the Comforter, if he went away from them in that bodily Appearance, which ſhould convince the World of Sin, Righteouſneſs and Judgment, if the Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the Spirit was already in the World, to convince them of Sin, Righteouſneſs and Judgment, and to comfort true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers:</hi> I anſwer, ſurely none will or can deny, who profeſs <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but the Apoſtles in ſome Meaſure before Chriſt's outward Departure from them, had the Comfort of the holy Spirit in them, and were both Believers and obedient Children in their Meaſure, when he ſent them forth in his Name before his Departure, and they returned rejoycing, becauſe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils were made ſubject, &amp;c. to that living Authority they were ſent forth in, and the World was alſo convinced of Sin, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Judgment in Meaſure, before the Promiſe of this ſending, and great pouring forth of the Spirit; but this was a fuller Miniſtration promiſed of Goſpel-Glory, both for the further and fuller Convincement of the World, and alſo the fuller Revelation of this great Myſtery to them, <hi>Chriſt within the Hope of Glory,</hi> for their exceeding great Satisfaction and Increaſe of that Comfort and Faith, which in ſome Meaſure they had before, and gifting and impowering them for that great Work whereunto they were appointed.</p>
            <p>And therefore all the World may ſee, that are not wilfully blind, that it alwayes was, and is, and will be the ſame forever that reveals the Comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, to ſuch as are true Believers in Chriſt Jeſus, and alſo convinces the <hi>World of Sin, Righteouſneſs and Judgment,</hi> the Principle is one, the Spirit of Truth, the Light, the VVord of Faith, the ſame forever, in all Ages and Generations, according to its Manifeſtation, that all through it believing, and by the Means of it, may know the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42502:7"/>
Lord and his Sufficiency forever; for by what Means do Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple come to ſee when they are tempted, or when Evil is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Hearts, and a Conſent of Heart is preſſed unto by the Enemy, doth not this Light of Chriſt in the Heart imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately give them VVarning? and by believing and hearkning to the Counſel of its Teaching, are they not preſerved even in Heart from Conſenting? and is not this an Act of true Faith, through the vertuous Blood of Jeſus? and is not this the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God's Power in Chriſt, made manifeſt in the Light, that gives <hi>Ability to reſiſt, and is greater in ſuch to preſerve out of Evil, then the Power of Darkneſs to prevail and lead into it. Oh that People would conſider what belongs to their Peace, and know the great God near them with his Light within, the Ground both of their Sight and Strength, to let them ſee Evil in its firſt Appearance, and give them preſent Power and Help againſt it, and that all may be aſhamed, who have lift up a Weapon againſt the Power and Sufficiency of its Teaching, and repent, is the true Deſire of him, who is a Lover of true Righteouſneſs,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtopher Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as <hi>VVilliam Haworth,</hi> an <hi>Independent</hi> Preacher, makes mention of my Name in his Reply to the Book written by <hi>John Crook</hi> and <hi>VVilliam Bayly,</hi> in Anſwer to his called, <hi>The</hi> Quaker <hi>converted;</hi> and it is there printed in his Epiſtle, That I called the Doctrine of Election a Deviliſh, Damnable and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Doctrine, which is a moſt wicked and notorious Lye, from the Father of Lyes, which is the Devil, who hath got ſuch Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Head in <hi>VVilliam Haworth's</hi> Heart, that he is grown deſperate and Fool-hardy: But I affirm, that <hi>W. H.</hi> in the hearing of <hi>Jeremy Swift</hi> of <hi>Hartford</hi> and another Man in his Priſon-Chamber there, we falling into Diſpute about the Doctrine of Election and Reprobation, and I asking him in theſe Words,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42502:8"/>
               <hi>Whether God ordained People to be wicked before they were born?</hi> anſwered, <hi>Yes,</hi> and did affirm it, which I might perhaps Juſtly call a Devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, Damnable and Blaſphemous Doctrine; and his I noted down in Writing, and afterwards writ a Paper and ſent to the afore-named <hi>Jeremy Swift,</hi> one of the Members of his Church, ſo called, wherein was mentioned this wicked Doctrine, with other of the ſame kind, but that ever I ſaid, the Doctrine of Election was a Damnable Doctrine, I utterly deny; and he knows in his own Conſcience, he notoriouſly belyes me; for in all our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings about ſuch Things, I affirmed both the Doctrine of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Reprobation according to Scripture, but that God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained People to be wicked before they were born; let him prove that damnable and wicked Doctrine, if he can, or elſe own him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a wicked <hi>Heathen</hi> and a <hi>Ranter;</hi> for if ſo, then God is the Author of all Wicked<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs.</p>
            <p>Alſo he ſaid, <hi>That I, with others of my Fellow-Priſoners, contended againſt Original Sin;</hi> unto which I anſwer,</p>
            <p>That I alwayes affirmed, that the Devil alwayes was, and is the Original of Sin in Mankind, who obey him; it was alwayes my Judgment, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned by hearkning to the Devil, and diſobeying the Counſel of the Lord; but how there can be any other kind of Sinning then through <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief and Diſobedience to God's Law and Goſpel, I know not, that is, how Innocents or Infants in the Womb of their Mothers, can ſin, or be guilty of Sin, until they have tranſgreſſed the Law of God, and contract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Guilt by that Means, I underſtand not: Therefore this Doctrine of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Infants in the Womb Tranſgreſſors, before they have done Evil, either in Thought, Word or Work, is a cruel unnatural Doctrine; and he ought to prove his Charge of Evil or Sin againſt them, or elſe be aſhamed, and charge Innocents no longer, until they have done Evil; for Thouſands and Ten Thouſands by this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Doctrine are condemned, who are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas he ſaith, <hi>how often did I hear this Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat in his Preaching, do this and Live,</hi> hereby inſinuating, as if I <hi>preſſed People to the Obſervance of</hi> Moſes's <hi>Law only in the Letter for Life, and did not preſs unto the Obedience of Faith in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which I anſwer,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42502:8"/>
            <p>That he never once heard me repeat ſo, but a lying Spirit hath poſſeſſed him, and from the Heart ſo poſſeſſed proceeds Lyes, but I alwayes directed to Chriſt Jeſus, the true Saviour, and his Light within, that through Faith in him, the true Light that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World, People might be ſaved, and be obedient to the Goſpel of Peace, and come to witneſs the good Work of Regeneration, and enter God's Kingdom; but he told me, as ſeveral can witneſs, <hi>That though a Man was regenerate and born again, and ſo might enter God's Kingdom, yet this was not ſufficient,</hi> nay, he call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d this Work of Regeneration <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>a Man's own Righteouſneſs;</hi> but this is ſo abominable and wicked a Doctrine, that ſurely none but Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and Infidels will believe; It is ſuch Nonſence, that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was never uttered, that a Man ſhould come into ſuch a State, through Faith in Chriſt Jeſus (without which it cannot be) as to be regenerate, and enter God's Kingdom, and yet this is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, then let him tell me what this Man entered into God's Kingdom, and ſo poſſeſſed of an Everlaſting Inheritance in Chriſt Jeſus, is further to do or believe for Sufficiency; is he not now a Poſſeſſor of the Everlaſting Inheritance in Chriſt Jeſus? Tell me what State is greater, and beyond this; nay, this (he ſaid) was <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs;</hi> what a Traytor is this Man to God and his Goſpel, who hath ſeemed in Words and Profeſſion thus far to hug and to love Chriſt and the Scriptures, and with his feigned Lips to betray him into the Hands of the vileſt of Men, and call this his moſt bleſſed Work of Regeneration, <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs, and a Man's own Righteouſneſs,</hi> thus betraying his moſt bleſſed Image into the Hands of Sinners, to be trampled upon, and vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and abuſed, under the Name of <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs, and a Man's own Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>ſo as filthy Rags,</hi> Iſa. 64. 6. and ſo conſoquently, Chriſt to be no more a Saviour upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, then the <hi>Jews</hi> accounted him, who only reckoned him the Carpenter's Son, and a Deceiver; for indeed, Man is meerly cheated of his Salvation, if this Work of Chriſt be no more but <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs;</hi> and Chriſt's Coming by this Means is made of no more Sufficiency, then to bring forth <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs;</hi> but this Man bears falſe Witneſs by his Lyes and Blaſphemies, as any who are truly <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may eaſily perceive. And as for his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42502:9"/>
ſaying, W. Penn <hi>told one of his Friends, that</hi> George Fox <hi>was as good a Prophet as</hi> Iſaiah (I have ſpoken with <hi>W. P.</hi> and he ſaith, that he never made ſuch a Compariſon to any of his Friends, either directly or indirectly, to the beſt of his Knowledge) <hi>and that he telling me of it, I affirmed the ſame,</hi> which I do not well remember; but however, what Abſurdity can there be in the Compariſon, to compare a bleſſed Goſpel-Miniſter with a bleſſed Prophet of the Lord; read <hi>Rom. 10. 15.</hi> where the Apoſtle quotes the Teſtimony of that bleſſed Prophet, <hi>Iſa. 52. 7. How beautiful are the Feet of them that preach the Goſpel of Peace, and bring glad Tidings of good Things;</hi> but <hi>G. F.</hi> that bleſſed Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt preached, and yet preacheth the Goſpel of Peace, and hath brought, and yet doth bring glad Tidings of good Things; and this though neither he, nor ſuch as he can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, yet we know it and affirm it, ſo that he hath been, and yet is a bleſſed Inſtrument in the Hand of the Lord. And as in one Part of his Book he ſaith, <hi>He asked me whether the Man Chriſt Jeſus was in me, and that I ſhould affirm he was;</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which I anſwer, That I never knew any other Chriſt Jeſus but one, the ſame Yeſterday, to Day, and forever, who in the Scripture is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Son of Man,</hi> whom I witneſs to be in me in Meaſure by his Spirit and Power, my Saviour to take away my Sin, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me from it, as I am kept in the true ſaving Faith of God's Elect; but if he would here inſinuate, as if I ſhould ſay, <hi>That that Body was in me, in which he then appeared,</hi> that is a groſs Lye; neither do I believe he did believe I meant ſo, becauſe he hath often heard from me to the contrary, how I alwayes affirmed Chriſt's Spiritual Appearance in me, &amp;c. So this in ſhort, I have anſwered at preſent, to correct a lying Tongue, and to bear my Witneſs againſt an Anti chriſtian Teacher, for ſo he certainly is, and will appear to be ſtill more by what he may bring forth, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his Pretences to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> except he repent; and his Deceit and his Hypocriſie is ſufficiently manifeſt to ſuch as fear the Lord; and further I may decipher this Man in Anſwer to his next Appearance if he be not yet ſatisfied; and he had never been thus publick from my Pen, if himſelf had not been the Cauſe of it; but I have more againſt him, then what I have here ſet down, or at preſent am willing to write concerning him, except neceſſity requires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtopher Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42502:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
